dr. auntie Galpin here and welcome back
to 5-minute phys a series where I take
important strength and conditioning
health or nutrition questions and I give
you the answer in five minutes or less
today what we're talking about is how to
pick the right exercise for your workout
programs now it doesn't matter if you're
doing this workout for yourself or if
you're designing this for someone else
or if you're actually a practising coach
the area I want to tackle today is
what's known as exercise choice now if
we look at the big picture of what's
called program designs this is what we
call what were the phrase we use and we
talk about designing your workout
programs what we realize is there are
seven classic modifiable variables and
we'll have another talk specifically on
all the modifiable variables but this is
a fancy way of saying these are all the
things that you can modify or all the
variables you can change that will alter
the results of the effectiveness of your
workout program and the one I want to
tackle today is get again that exercise
choice so what information do I use and
how do I make the best possible choice
on which exercises I do or don't do or
probably more appropriately which
variation of what exercises I do so in
other words I've decided I want to squat
today well do I squat to a front squat a
back squat do I use dumbbell a barbell a
cambered bar a safety squat bar maybe I
use a kettlebell a goblet squat
one-legged two-legged things like that
understanding exercise choice is
developed to help us understand the
nuances of the differences between all
of those exercises so that we can select
the exact one we want and more probably
more importantly not ones we don't want
a friend of mine said this wonderful
years ago and he said you know the real
true test of an if you to know if you
have an excellent coach or not is asked
that very clearly you know why did we
select that exercise why am i doing that
exercise and if their answer is
something like well we we deadlift
because it's important it's a big
movement it's a probably a pretty good
indicator that your coach doesn't really
understand that choice right the answer
to that question should be well we
wanted to get x y&z I wanted to avoid a
B
C+ last week we did GE F and ear I'm out
order there but you get the idea right
or what's coming up next but you're
history
and then you start to go okay this coach
really understands exercise selection so
of course I'm not gonna cover the entire
thing today I will have expanded
versions of this talk in 25 minute fizz
and 55-minute fizz so check those out
for more detail but just as a quick
oversight this is a test of learning to
see how well you understand this bigger
concept so take a look at these two
exercises these are both variations of
the squat and depending on how detailed
you want to get down these things but
the one on the side over here would be
classic barbell overhead squat over here
is a funny variation where I have a
kettlebell in one hand it's a one-handed
one-legged on a medicine ball squat it's
just a fancier version of the overhead
squat so when I ask you right now and I
want to see what your instincts are
which exercise is better now a mediocre
level coach or a bad coach would have an
answer for this and they would say
either how will this overhead barbell
squats better cuz you can lift more
weights or something or another coach
might say actually this single armed
state one footed version is better
because it requires more stability well
as well see in a later video there are
no such things as good or bad exercises
it's all situationally dependent so what
I would say is exercise choice is not
necessarily knowing which exercises are
good or bad and more about what exactly
is good about it what is exactly or what
exactly is bad about it and when can I
apply this based on my situation so a
few things to consider and I gave you 11
here this is certainly no means every
single thing you should ever consider or
all-inclusive but things like what are
the muscles involved in the exercise
alright so if I'm looking to engage say
my my shoulders more and get a heavier
heart or shoulder workout
perhaps a barbell overhead squat is
better because I can load it a lot
heavier than I can a one-armed
one-footed on a
medicine ball squat because I have so
much instability all right other things
to consider the persons anthropometrics
so do they have a short femur long torso
things like that you also have practical
considerations so a lot of times it's
important to change your variety or pick
different exercises simply for the sake
of variety because you're bored or tired
or demotivated from doing things right
and then of course the last thing in
your list is always ideal versus
realistic I'm fortunate enough to work
with a lot of combat sport athletes and
I would ideally I would love for them to
do a barbell overhead squat and snatches
realistically though they're in the hurt
sport meaning they hurt people for a
living meaning they get hurt for a
living if anything in your body hurts
you can't do a barbell snatch so
although it's ideal for me to make that
exercise choice of a snatch it's not
very realistic in that population
alright so take a look at all these
things I encourage you to think through
them and actually go ahead and put
together a small program for yourself or
maybe even for a week and make your
exercise selections try to encompass all
11 of these things in your
considerations when you're doing that
that's it for now if you enjoyed that
check out the follow up videos or other
videos I've made in my website and egapp
and Comm follow me on Twitter Instagram
and all the such to share these things
around and that's it for now we'll see
you next time
you